<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Another great and bloudy fight in the North, between the forces under the command of James Duke of Hambleton, Lord Generall of the Scottish Army, and the Parliaments forces under the immediate conduct of Major Gen. Lambert, upon Wednesday last neer the borders of Yorkshire. With the particulars of the said fight, and the number that were killed, and cullers taken, and the Scots resolution concerning Lieut. Gen. Cromwell. Also, the E of Calender marched into Northumberland, with Deer Saundy Hambleton the Scots famous engineer; and their resolution touching Colchester. Likewise, sad and dangerous tydings from Colchester, and the sallying out of Sir Charles Lucas upon the Parliaments forces, his digging of great trenches to swallow them up, and their resolution to maintain their works to an inch of ground.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 10 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75388</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3263</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E456_5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R170</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860132</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860132</idno>
            <idno type="VID">112240</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75388)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 112240)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 72:E456[5])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Another great and bloudy fight in the North, between the forces under the command of James Duke of Hambleton, Lord Generall of the Scottish Army, and the Parliaments forces under the immediate conduct of Major Gen. Lambert, upon Wednesday last neer the borders of Yorkshire. With the particulars of the said fight, and the number that were killed, and cullers taken, and the Scots resolution concerning Lieut. Gen. Cromwell. Also, the E of Calender marched into Northumberland, with Deer Saundy Hambleton the Scots famous engineer; and their resolution touching Colchester. Likewise, sad and dangerous tydings from Colchester, and the sallying out of Sir Charles Lucas upon the Parliaments forces, his digging of great trenches to swallow them up, and their resolution to maintain their works to an inch of ground.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 6 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for generall satisfaction,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 31".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Army --  Early works to 1800'.</term>
               <term>Scotland. --  Army --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Colchester (England) --  History --  Siege, 1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:112240:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Another great and bloudy FIGHT IN THE NORTH, BETWEEN The Forces under the command of <hi>James</hi> Duke of <hi>Hamble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> Lord Generall of the Scottiſh Army, and the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments Forces under the immediate conduct of Major Gen. <hi>Lambert,</hi> upon Wedneſday laſt neer the Borders of Yorkſhire.</p>
            <p>WITH The particulars of the ſaid Fight, and the number that were killed, and Cullers taken, and the Scots reſolution con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Lieut. Gen. <hi>Cromwell.</hi> Alſo, the E of <hi>Calender</hi> marched into <hi>Northumberland,</hi> with <hi>Deer Saundy Hambleton</hi> the Scots famous Engineer; and their Reſolution touching <hi>Colcheſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LIKEWISE, Sad and dangerous Tydings from <hi>Colcheſter,</hi> and the ſallying out of Sir <hi>Charles Lucas</hi> upon the Parliaments Forces, his digging of great Trenches to ſwallow them up, and their reſolution to maintain their Works to an inch of ground.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London</hi> Printed for generall ſatisfaction, 1648.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:112240:2"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
               </gap> ſwer them again, with the ſame which they meat to us; and I believe they have paid for their ſallying at a high rate: for we have killed about twenty of the troop called the ſhavers, Sir Charles Lucas his Major, and divers others of eminency, the loſſe of whom they much lament, VVe have alſo killed their chief Gunner, and our great Guns playes hard upon them, doing great execution. The laſt night they made another ſally, and thought to have ſurpriſed ſome of our Guards, but by timely diſcovery were prevented, and made good their retreat without loſſe.</p>
            <p>Thoſe who come out of the town ſay, they begin to eate horſe fleſh, whether for need, or as a dainty, we know not: they are afraid of a ſtorm, and in that reſpect have provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded whatever may defend themſelves or offend us. They dig deep holes in almoſt all the ſtreets of this town, that ſo if we ſtorm, our horſe ſhould be uſeleſſe; the high ſtreet is not pittied, for there they feed their horſes, giving them graſſe and nay upon ſtalls belonging to the ſhops.</p>
            <p>It is further reported, that they have made two inner VVorkes within the walls, and have dug a deep trench under them, at leaſt four yards deep, that in eaſe our men ſhould ſtorm, their trenches ſhould be the Gulfe to ſwallow them: in conſideration whereof, it is conceived it will be very dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult work to accompliſh, and prejudiciall for our Army to ſtorm; but we doubt not but to force them to conditions for ſurrender in a ſhort time, or elſe become Maſter, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of by a famine in the town. The enemy maintains their quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters well, they diſpute every inch of ground, but in open places they are not ſo valiant. VVee are put to exceeding hard duty for want of our own Soldiers.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Caeſar</hi> fought againſt <hi>Pompey</hi> in <hi>Greece,</hi> whoſe Army was not come to him, onely a numerous company unexperienc'd Roman gallants, <hi>Caeſar</hi> got the better, and gave
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:112240:2"/>this accyunt, he found the Generail with an Army, many of the priſoners and dying Enemies, ſay that their plot was to bring in the King upon the Parliament, not bp treaty but force, the means to effect it was by making the Parliament odious, and chus to aſperſe them with reproaches from all ſorts of Pamphlets, whereby the people ſhould be incenſed againſt them, 2. To ſtir up the people to p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tition acd muti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. 3 Togather into arms, that then Cavaliers who were to be confided in, carry on the work and not raw diſcontented countrey men, who onely long for peace. To weaken the Army by making them odious, putting them upon action in all parts, that they appear formidable no where, nor able to reſiſt numerous riſings. 5 To make moſt noiſe there where there was leaſt deſign to fright the Parliament with the Scots comming, when the intention was to be ſtrongeſt in the South. 6 To raiſe, if not deſtroy the Parl. or force them to yield to the King.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Colchester</hi> 
                  <date>July 29. 1648.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>There is a great Rumour amongſt the Royaliſts in Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, that Major Gen. Lambert is totally routed, and that He hath loſt 17. Foot Cullers, and 9 of Horſe; which Report is falſe, ſome skirmiſhing hath been between them, and the Major General (as we hear) is retreated towards Cleveland: for your further ſatisfaction, I refer you to the incloſed Letter.</p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:112240:3"/>
            <head>Terrible News from the North, being a true Relation of another great Fight between the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and the <hi>Scots neer Yorkſhire.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>DUke <hi>Hamilton</hi> is upon his march towards <hi>Bowes</hi> and <hi>Stainmore,</hi> and thought to have forced his way at <hi>Stainmore</hi> paſſage, but was preſented; for Major Generall <hi>Lambert</hi> having placed a very conſiderable party to ſecure the ſaid Bridge and paſſage, and a Briggade of the Scots comming up, thinking to paſſe the River, found oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, and the quarrell diſputed for the ſpace of two hours and had not another Briggade of the Scots come up, we had been Maſters of the day; but ſeeing our ſelvs over-pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, made an honourable retreat towards Barnard Caſtle, which was ſix or ſeven miles diſtant from us, the enemy purſued about three miles, but at a diſtant, they over-powr us exceedingly in Foot, and have great numbers of horſe. In this conflict we loſt about 30. men, and brought off about 20 which were wounded; the loſſe of the enemy is thought to be far more.</p>
            <p>We are daily in action, and have hard duty, our numbers being not potent enough. We expect Lieutenant Gen. <hi>Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel</hi> and his Forces dayly, whom the Scots ſay they will ſoundly cudgell, and are reſolved to fight him, though he be never ſo ſtrong. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ndeed, they have a very potent Army, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, they expect 3000. from Major Generall <hi>Monro,</hi> and another Army from <hi>Scotland,</hi> to march by the way of <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:112240:3"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Thorney</hi> houſe is ſurrendred to Col. <hi>Charles Fairfax,</hi> by the Bees of <hi>Pentefract.</hi> A Narrative of their proceedings, I have here inſerted, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>Col. Fairfax his Letter to Col. Pauldin Governour of Thorney houſe for the King.</head>
            <p>Sir, I am ingaged to make good my proffer. The Renditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Thornhil houſe wil forfeit no Loyalty; though blood be precious, yet we cannot condeſcend to ſo long a ceſſation as to expect any anſwer from Pontefract, but a ſpeedy ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render to.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>C. Fairfax.</signed>
               <dateline>Thornhill <date>16 of July, 1648.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>To the Governour of Thornhill Hall.</head>
            <p>Sir, <hi>You may not expect any thing here but what you can win with your Sword, untill I receive further commands from my Superiours.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours, <hi>Thomas Paulden.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <p>Sir, If God ſhall give you ſo compaſſionate a heart to pity the lives of ſo many of your Souldiers, with divers others that be now in your Garriſon, we ſhall become humble ſuiters unto the Parliament (whoſe former mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies ſome of you have liberally taſted) that you may have the latitude of favour, whereof your ſeveral conditions wil admit you capable. But if our offer be now rejected, you muſt expect a purſuance of our advantages with all extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity. And be aſſured the blood of thoſe that dy in the ſlaughter, (a work we abhor, if you did not inforce it) wil be required at your hands, and of them that adviſe you.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>C. Fairfax.</signed>
               <dateline>Thornhill <date>18. July, 1648.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> To infer your concluſion, that the bloud ſpilt ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired at our hands, before you have proued that we ought not to defend, <hi>our right and the Kings,</hi> with our blood, is very
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:112240:4"/>bad logick; your Rhetorick not ſo pregnant, as may perſwade us to aſsent to ſo diſhonourable conditions, upon ſo ſmall reaſon; but in order to the tenderneſſe we have of Chriſtian blood, if you pleaſe to appoint two of like condition with ours mentioned in my Letters to Sir Henry Cholmley, and ſend us Hostages, we ſhall imbrace a Parley. This is all can be returned from,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your ſervant, <hi>Thomas Palden.</hi>
               </signed>
               <date>July 18. 1648.</date>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>To Collonel <hi>Fairfax</hi> theſe preſent.</head>
            <p>The Earl of <hi>Kalender</hi> Lieut. Gen. to Duke <hi>Hambleton</hi> is marched over <hi>Berwick</hi> bridge into <hi>England,</hi> with a ſecond Army conſiſting of about 8000. with whom comes <hi>Deere Saundy Hambleton</hi> the famous Engineer the L. <hi>Lanerick</hi> is Governour of the town of <hi>Berwick.</hi> We hear that they have fallen upon Col. <hi>Lilburns</hi> quarters in <hi>Northumberland,</hi> took about 27. priſoners, 50. horſe, and two Cullers. It is ſaid, that they intend to march directly for <hi>Colche<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ter,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Barnard Castle</hi> 
                  <date>July 27. 1648.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
